GHCN-Monthly, Version 4, Status File 

(users can use this file to determine overall current status, including 
information related to previous changes and errata).

DISCLAIMER: The status file does not record every possible change that may
have occurred from one version to another.  This would be impractical for a
variety of reasons. Therefore if a user is interested in discovering every 
possible difference between two different file versions, they will need to 
construct their own program to determine all possible changes between the file
versions. 

********************************************************************************

10/26/2018

GHCN-M version 4.0.0 is now operational. Issues may still arise during the 
first few days of operations. For any questions, please email
ncdc.ghcnm@noaa.gov

********************************************************************************

09/24/2018

With the early online release of the GHCN-M v4 paper, this product is being 
transitioned from a public beta (v4.b.2) to operations (v4.0.0). During this
transition, issues may arise with data output. For questions, please email
ncdc.ghcnm@noaa.gov 

********************************************************************************

02/16/2018

Beginning with the 20180215 run, a third version of v4 beta will be produced.
In addition to QCU and QCF, a QFE inventory and data file will be generated.
The QFE includes estimated data for stations for the period of 1961-1990. Data
are estimated based upon neighboring station info in the Pairwise Homogeneity
Algorithm (PHA). Data is only provided between 1961 and 1990, and will be used
to assess climate trends.

********************************************************************************

11/22/2017

An update to the public BETA of GHCN-M version 4 has been made available, known
as v4.b.2. Changes include:

    - Incorporating the update from the ISTI Databank, now at version 1.1.1.
    - Incorporating changes and updates to the quality control procedure. For
      more information about the flags, please refer to the readme file.
    - Other minor bug fixes, as pointed out from the user community.

Please remember this is still a beta version of GHCN-M version 4, which is 
undergoing final testing before its official release. The underlying
data, its software and all content are provided on an 'as is' and 'as available'
basis. We do not give any warranties, whether express or implied, as to the
suitability or usability of the product, its software or any of its content.

Feedback is welcome and should be sent via email to:
ncdc.ghcnm@noaa.gov

Should you have any questions or concerns regarding the product,
please let us know immediately so we can rectify these accordingly.
Your help in this regard is greatly appreciated.

********************************************************************************

07/20/2017

Beginning this week, v4 beta will begin ingesting new data and adjusting it 
through the Pairwise Homogeneity Algorithm. This update essentially reverts the
change that was made on March 20th, 2017.

********************************************************************************

03/20/2017

Starting with the 20170310 run, v4 Beta will stop adjusting new data ingested. 
Instead, quality controlled unadjusted (QCU) data will be appended
to both QCU and QCF files of v4 beta. During the first month of the new year,
the Pairwise Homogenity Adjustment (PHA) will be run again to adjust the datasets
entire period of record. 

********************************************************************************

10/15/2015

A public BETA of GHCN-M version 4 has been made available,
effective 10/15/2015. This is the first beta distribution, and its version
is known as v4.b.1

Please note that this is a beta version of GHCN-M version 4, which is
still undergoing final testing before its official release. The underlying
data, its software and all content are provided on an 'as is' and 'as available' 
basis. We do not give any warranties, whether express or implied, as to the 
suitability or usability of the product, its software or any of its content.

Feedback is welcome and should be sent via email to:
ncdc.ghcnm@noaa.gov

Should you have any questions or concerns regarding the product,
please let us know immediately so we can rectify these accordingly.
Your help in this regard is greatly appreciated.